You know, usually like when you look at a map of a city, you see the streets, you see the buildings, the parks, it all makes intuitive sense.
Right. You can just trace a line from point A to point B.
Exactly. You trace a line from your house to your office and the map provides this cohesive, unified picture of reality.
But I want you to imagine for a second, if depending on what street you turn down, the actual foundational laws of the universe just, well, they just completely changed.
That would be terrifying.
It would be like you're walking down your own block and physics works normally, right?
Gravity pulls you down. Momentum pushes you forward.
But then you cross an intersection into a different neighborhood and suddenly the laws of thermodynamics are totally inverted.
Heat flows from cold to hot.
And then you turn a corner into the financial district and time itself is running backwards.
Cause and effect have basically swapped places.
I mean, navigating a space like that wouldn't just be confusing.
It would be fundamentally impossible.
If the underlying logic of reality shifts every single time you cross a boundary, there's no shared baseline to make a decision.
You couldn't build a bridge, let alone, you know, a functioning society.
And yet when you really step back and look at how we understand our world today, that is exactly the intellectual landscape we live in.
We exist in this deeply, deeply fragmented reality.
We really do.
Because if you ask a physicist to explain the universe, they give you this system of, you know, cold, hard causality, deterministic equations, maybe some quantum probabilities.
Yeah, it's all very mechanical.
Right.
But if you walk over to the economics department, they give you a world of rational actors, numerical value, transactional equilibrium.
And then there's the philosophy department.
Exactly.
You sit alone in a quiet room and just examine your own subjective human experience.
Like, the actual feeling of making a difficult choice or the sensation of time passing.
And neither the physicist nor the economist can explain what is actually happening to you.
Not at all.
These frameworks all seem to operate by completely different, totally incompatible rules.
It's a profound structural disconnect.
Because physics has essentially, well, no room for human agency.
Economics struggles to account for actual human meaning or qualitative well-being or, you know, ecological reality.
Yeah.
The stuff that actually matter.
Right.
And philosophy is just perpetually stuck in the middle, endlessly trying to figure out how your rich, internal, subjective experience of, like, listening to this conversation right now,
how that could possibly arise from the blind mechanical interactions of atoms and molecules in your brain.
Which brings us to our mission for this deep dive.
Today, we are exploring this truly radical paper published in March, 2026 by an author named Fliction.
It's titled Process, Projection, and Power Toward a Unified Ontology of Choice, Causality, and Value.
Quite a mouthful.
It is, and the ambition here is just staggering.
Because this paper is attempting to build what it calls a unified ontology.
A single, cohesive, mathematical, and philosophical framework that can explain all of it.
All the different neighborhoods on that map you mentioned.
Exactly.
We're going to explore the deepest mysteries of the flow of time and human consciousness.
Map that onto how you and I actually make choices.
See how the invention of money fundamentally distorts the geometry of those choices.
And finally...
The really dense part.
Oh yeah.
Finally, look at a highly technical mathematical blueprint the author proposes for saving complex systems from total collapse.
And I think it's crucial to lay out the core thesis right up front.
The author argues that the reason we have all these disconnected, incompatible maps of reality is that for centuries, our traditional frameworks have been looking at the universe entirely backward.
Backward how?
Well, in classical science, we've treated reality as being made up of static objects or static states.
We think the universe is fundamentally made of things.
You know, particles, planets, people, dollars.
And then just occasionally those things change.
So like a universe made of billiard balls just sitting on a table waiting for the cue ball to strike them.
The being is the default and the doing is secondary.
Exactly.
Yeah.
But this paper completely inverts that paradigm.
It argues that transitions, like processes, choices, the irreversible changes from one state to another, those are the actual fundamental building blocks of reality.
Wow.
Yeah.
Everything we think of as a static thing is actually just a secondary projection.
It's a temporary shadow cast by an underlying continuous process.
It's an ontology of becoming rather than an ontology of being.
Okay.
Let's unpack this.
We have a massive intellectual journey ahead of us.
And before we really get into the mechanics, I just want to emphasize to you, the listener, that this paper touches on some incredibly heavy systemic topics.
Yeah.
It really goes there.
It analyzes capitalism, the consolidation of corporate power, economic extraction, institutional decay.
But our goal today is not to take any political sides or endorse any specific ideological viewpoint.
Absolutely not.
We are going to explore these concepts strictly as the formal, structural, and mathematical mechanics proposed by the author.
We're treating this as an exploration of a deeply complex architectural model.
Our job is simply to convey the fascinating structural arguments contained in the source material, regardless of where they point.
Because the math doesn't care about politics.
It cares about structure.
And if we want to understand how a structure as complex as a global finance or systemic power operates within this new process ontology, we actually have to start at the very bottom.
The very bottom.
Yeah.
We have to start with one of the most famous intractable problems in all of science.
You're talking about the hard problem of consciousness.
The very one.
So for anyone listening who might not, you know, spend their weekends reading cognitive science journals, the standard hard problem was famously formulated by the philosopher David Chalmers.
It basically asks, how does physical matter create the rich, subjective, qualitative experience of being alive?
Like, we can map the neural correlates of the brain.
We can see exactly how the visual cortex processes the wavelength of red light.
But none of that mechanical data explains what it actually feels like to see the color red.
The actual experience.
Yeah.
How do blind, unfeeling neurons firing in the dark of your skull turn into the taste of coffee or the feeling of grief?
And for decades, scientists and philosophers have just banged their heads against the wall, trying to solve this by looking for some missing mechanism in the brain.
But Fliction's paper argues that the hard problem isn't actually about how matter makes mind at all.
No?
No.
The paper proposes that the hard problem is entirely a categorical mismatch about time.
A mismatch about time.
Okay.
That is a massive pivot from standard neuroscience.
Let's break down what the paper means by that, starting with how physics views time.
Sure.
If we look at fundamental physics, what the paper calls the third-person perspective, time is entirely symmetric.
In the mathematical models of general relativity, for example, time is just another coordinate.
It's literally no different than up, down, left, or right.
So spatial.
Exactly.
All moments, past, present, and future, they're equally real and equally accessible in the math.
There is basically no mathematical variable in fundamental physics for the concept of now.
So, to a physicist looking purely at the equations, the universe is just this giant frozen block of four-dimensional space-time.
The Big Bang, the Roman Empire, you listening to this deep dive right now, and the eventual heat death of the universe,
they all just exist statically within the geometry of the math.
Yeah.
It's often called the block universe theory.
From that third-person objective view, nothing is technically happening.
Everything simply is.
Okay.
But your lived experience, the first-person perspective, is entirely different.
The reality you and I inhabit is strictly asymmetric.
The past is completely fixed and inaccessible.
The future is completely open and unwritten, and you're trapped forever in this ever-moving, razor-thin sliver of experience called now.
I was trying to visualize this profound disconnect when I was reading the paper, and here is how I think of it.
Imagine you're watching a movie on a streaming service, right?
Okay, yeah.
The third-person perspective, the physics perspective, is the entire progress bar at the bottom of the screen.
Every scene, from the opening credits to the finale, exists simultaneously on the server as data.
To the server, there's no fundamental difference between minute 10 and minute 90.
They're just spatial coordinates on a hard drive.
That is a highly functional way to visualize the block universe.
Thanks.
And the first-person perspective.
The first-person perspective is the actual playhead.
It's the laser or the processing unit reading the data moment to moment.
It only ever experiences one single frame at a time.
It leaves a trail of watched frames behind it.
That's the fixed past.
And it looks toward an unplayed buffer, the open future.
Right.
The progress bar is symmetric, but the playhead's journey is aggressively asymmetric.
It only moves in one direction.
And this is exactly where the paper identifies the root of our fragmented reality.
How has science historically dealt with this massive disconnect between the progress bar and the playhead?
It usually sides with the progress bar, doesn't it?
Exactly.
Classical science usually treats the timeless symmetric progress, bar the objective math, as the ultimate fundamental truth of reality.
And therefore, it treats your experience of the playhead.
The feeling of time flowing, of making choices, of moving from the present into the future.
It treats that as just a stubborn, persistent illusion created by human biology.
It says that your feeling of now is just a trick of the brain.
Right.
But this paper flips that completely upside down.
It is a total ontological inversion.
The paper argues that the first person lived experience of time flowing.
That irreversible transition from potentiality into actuality is the primary foundational feature of reality.
Wow.
The symmetric progress bar of physics is just an abstraction.
It's a model we build from our position at the playhead to try and understand the patterns of what we've already watched.
The transition is real.
The static block is the illusion.
Okay, if we accept this premise, that the transition, the flow of time itself, is the fundamental building block of the universe, what is it made of?
How does the paper define a transition mathematically?
Because it breaks this down into three irreducible elements, which it calls the triad of reality.
Causality, choice, and change.
In a traditional deterministic worldview, you only really have causality.
State A inevitably and mechanically leads to state B.
But Fliction argues that mathematically, you cannot derive the actual lived flow of reality without all three of these elements interacting.
Let's walk through the mechanics of the triad.
First, we have causality.
But it's not the old billiard ball causality, is it?
No.
In this framework, causality represents the third-person structure.
It is the set of allowed future possibilities.
Given the current state of the universe, the underlying laws dictate a menu of possible next states.
Causality doesn't pick what happens next.
It strictly defines the boundaries of what is mathematically allowed to happen next.
It writes the menu.
Then comes the second element.
Choice.
And I want to be very careful here, because we aren't just talking about human beings pondering what to eat for lunch.
Choice, in this generalized ontological sense, is the first-person agency.
It is the specific selection operator that picks one single path from that menu of causal possibilities.
It is the mechanism that collapses the multiple potentials into a singular direction.
And finally, change.
Change is the irreversible actualization of that choice into history.
It is the permanent act of taking that select impossibility and appending it to the record of the past, rendering it completely fixed and unalterable.
Now, I have to push back here, because if you have a background in physics, your alarm bells are probably ringing right now.
Oh, absolutely.
If physics says the universe is governed by fundamental forces and quantum mechanics, where does choice actually live in the math?
Are we suggesting that human free will or some cosmic consciousness is magically altering the trajectory of atoms in defiance of physics?
It's a vital skepticism.
The paper is absolutely not arguing for magic.
This is where it introduces one of its most elegant mathematical concepts to bridge the gap.
The dual aspect of indeterminacy, or what it calls the hard randomness symmetry.
Let's dig into the math of this.
How does the paper reconcile indeterminate quantum events with the concept of choice?
Think about a highly unpredictable event.
This could be a quantum superposition collapsing, or a highly complex non-linear event in a human neural network.
There's a transition that cannot be perfectly predicted simply by looking at the past states.
An indeterminate transition, we don't know exactly what will happen until it happens.
Right.
Now, how do we describe that event?
The paper proves mathematically that an external third-person observer, someone looking at this system from the outside, can only describe this unpredictable event using a probability distribution.
Because they can't see the whole picture.
Exactly.
To the outside observer, it looks like randomness or stochastic noise.
They lack the internal contextual information, so they just see a dice roll.
They see a 70% chance of outcome A and a 30% chance of outcome B.
Because they are looking at the menu.
They are studying the causality.
Yes.
But, and this is the theoretical breakthrough, a first-person observer looking from the inside of that exact same system, experiencing that exact same indeterminate transition, experiences it as choice.
Whoa.
Randomness and choice are not two different phenomena fighting for control of the universe.
They are two different informational descriptions of the exact same event.
I want to make sure the listener really grasps this, because it's mind-bending.
The paper uses category theory to formalize this, specifically pointing to adjoint functors.
Now, in mathematics, a functor is basically a mapping that translates the structure of one mathematical category into another.
Precisely.
It preserves the relationships between objects when you move them to a new context.
So, if I understand the paper's proof, it's saying that when you apply a forgetful functor, meaning you strip away the internal, subjective, first-person context of an event to look at it objectively, the math literally collapses into pure probability.
It becomes randomness.
randomness.
Yes.
But when you apply the free functor, adding the internal lived context back into the equation, that exact same mathematical event resolves into the geometry of choice.
It's the exact mechanism.
They're dual aspects.
Like, if I'm watching you deliberate over a difficult career decision, I cannot possibly compute the entirety of your internal state.
To me, from the outside, you have a probabilistic chance of quitting your job or staying.
It looks like a stochastic equation.
Sure.
But inside your mind, you aren't rolling a die.
You are weighing the options, feeling the friction of the decision, and actively selecting a path.
So, the randomness I see is just the shadow cast by your internal choice, simply because I don't have access to your first-person perspective.
Yes.
And this brings us to the paper's ultimate, staggering conclusion about the hard problem.
Consciousness is not some magical substance or emergent smoke generated by complex brain matter.
Consciousness is the internal experience of temporal asymmetry.
It is simply what it feels like from the inside to resolve multiple possibilities into a single irreversible history.
If you are the playhead moving across the data, consciousness is the friction of that movement.
Exactly.
It's the sensation of the transition itself that completely reshapes how we view our place in the universe.
We aren't objects that have consciousness.
We are the active process of time flowing.
It shifts the foundation entirely.
Reality isn't a static collection of objects.
It is an endless sequence of choices resolving into irreversible history.
But that creates a massive new problem.
If reality is just this endless sequence of choices, who or what is actually making them?
In a framework where objects don't fundamentally exist, we have to completely throw out our traditional definition of what a person is.
We do.
Which brings us to the paper's second major phase, redefining the self and the geometry of possibility.
If we accept the premise that processes are fundamental, you cannot define yourself by your physical body.
I mean, your cells replace themselves constantly.
Your physical state is always in flux.
Right.
You also cannot define yourself as a static, unchanging soul floating somewhere outside of time.
So how does flexion define the human identity?
Because the paper introduces this formal mathematical definition of the self, represented as an ordered pair.
The equation is S sub T equals H sub T omega sub T.
Let's translate this into English for the listener.
The first variable, H sub T, is your history.
And the second variable, omega sub T, is your horizon.
History and horizon.
Let's start with history.
H sub T.
Your history is the irreversible, append-only record of every event, every choice, and every
transition that has ever happened to you or been made by you.
It is the absolute sum of your past, recorded in strict chronological order.
Crucially, in this math, history can never be erased, altered, or uncollapsed.
It is permanently fixed.
Okay, and based on that fixed history, we get the second variable, omega sub T, the horizon.
The horizon is your constrained space of possible futures.
It is the specific, mathematically defined set of possibilities that are open to you right
now in this exact moment, based entirely on what has happened in your history.
To help visualize this, let's think about how an RPG video game works, with those complex
skill trees, or like a massive branching narrative.
Let's use the concept of a high-dimensional manifold, or a phase space.
Imagine your life is a point moving through this massive, multidimensional web of paths.
Your history, your H sub T, is the exact unchangeable red line you've drawn through that web from the
moment you were born up until today.
And because you walk down that specific red line, you are standing at a very specific intersection
right now.
Right.
And your horizon, omega sub T, consists of the specific streets branching out in front of you
from this exact intersection.
Like, if you spent your history studying medicine, the become a surgeon path is open and illuminated
in your horizon.
If I didn't study medicine, that path physically does not exist in my omega sub T.
It is completely inaccessible to me.
So the paper is arguing that myself is not my body or my thoughts.
Myself is literally just the combination of the specific path I've walked and the specific
set of roads I am now mathematically allowed to choose from.
That is the structural reality of identity in this framework.
But the paper takes it a massive step further.
It's not just that your history dictates which options are available.
Your history actively dictates how you feel about those options and how likely you are
to take them.
This is where the author introduces preference fields, denoted mathematically as psi sub T.
Perference fields.
This sounds like we're applying the physics of gravity to human desires.
That is essentially what the math is doing.
The paper models this using what calls RSVP field dynamics, which stands for scalar density,
vector flow, and entropy fields.
Let's ground that math for the listener.
If I am standing at my intersection of choices, how does an RSVP field actually work on me?
Imagine your horizon of possibilities isn't a flat map, but a physical, topological landscape.
It has hills and valleys.
When you make a choice to walk down a certain path, you don't just move to a new location.
Your action physically deforms the landscape.
The scalar density represents the accumulation of your past choices.
The more you choose a certain type of response, the more mass that choice accumulates.
And in physics, mass creates gravity.
It bends the space around it.
Exactly.
Or, to use a more terrestrial analogy, imagine walking through a really dense forest.
The first time you bushwhack a path, it is incredibly difficult.
There is high friction, but the mere act of walking it presses down the grass and breaks
the branches.
The next time you face a similar choice, that path represents a vector flow of lesser resistance.
The dirt path is physically easier to walk down than hacking through the jungle again?
Yes.
Your prior choices create a gravitational pull towards similar choices in the future.
The field of your possibilities has been topologically deformed.
The entropy variable in the RSVP dynamics measures how much your horizon is narrowing or broadening
based on those grooves.
So, your preferences aren't just abstract, floating ideas in your mind.
They are structural modifications to the geometry of your future.
This has profound implications for how we think about human behavior.
If I choose to react to a stressful situation at work with, say, intense anger today, I'm not
just having an emotional moment.
Mathematically, I am digging a trench in my possibility space.
Exactly.
Tomorrow, when I face another stressor, the anger path is physically wider and steeper in
my mathematical horizon.
The vector flow is pushing me that way.
I am more likely to fall down it.
It's a formal geometric explanation for habits, neuroplasticity, and even addiction.
It completely bridges the gap between the psychology of habit and the mathematics of probability.
Yourself is a dynamic, constantly evolving geometry of choices.
So, I am my fixed history, my specific menu of future options, and the gravitational trenches
I've dug in that menu.
I exist as a geometric shape in a space of possibilities.
But this raises the ultimate problem of human existence.
What's that?
That mathematical model works perfectly for me sitting alone in a room.
Yeah.
But what happens when I walk out my front door and need to interact with you?
You have your own history, your own complex branching roads, and your own deep trenches.
We have completely different, totally subjective possibility spaces.
How on earth do we ever coordinate?
And this right here is the hinge of the entire paper.
This exact question, the collision of subjective possibility spaces, is how the author brilliantly
transitions from the quantum physics of consciousness directly into the brutal realities of macroeconomics.
Because to coordinate, we have to interact.
Yeah.
And when my geometry collides with your geometry, things get incredibly complicated.
When multiple agents with different possibility spaces need to interact, they merge to create
what the paper calls an aggregate possibility structure.
It is a massive, incredibly complex, high-dimensional web of overlapping histories, desires, physical
limitations, and potential futures.
If my life is a 3D landscape of paths, society is billions of those landscapes stacked on top
of each other, intercepting in impossible ways.
Yes.
And navigating that high-dimensional aggregate structure is cognitively impossible for human
beings.
Right.
We just do not have the computational power.
If you want to trade a loaf of bread for a pair of shoes, you cannot compute the deep historical
resonance, the ecological impact, the labor history, and the future implications of that
interaction for both you and the shoemaker.
The information density is just way too high.
The friction of the playhead would grind to a halt.
We would be paralyzed by the complexity of the math.
So human beings invent a tool to do the computing for us, to compress the aggregate possibility
space into something we can quickly navigate.
We invent money.
And I have to say, of all the theories of money I've read in economics, money as a store of
value, money as a medium of exchange, money as a ledger of debt, this paper's mathematical
definition is by far the most fascinating.
It redefines money not as a physical object or even a social belief, but as a mathematical
function.
It defines money formally as a projection functor, denoted as M sub T.
We talked about functors earlier when discussing consciousness.
A functor maps one complex category of math onto another.
So how does the money functor work?
The money functor takes this unbelievably complex, multidimensional web of human beings.
Human possibilities, relationships, ecological realities, and historical context.
And it projects all of it down into a single one-dimensional scalar number.
A price.
A monetary value.
It takes the giant, tangled, high-dimensional knot of human society and flattens it into a
single line.
A number on a spreadsheet.
It collapses the structural complexities so that we can coordinate quickly.
It answers the incredibly difficult question of, how much of my possibility space do I need
to sacrifice to access this specific part of your possibility space with a simple integer?
It is a brilliant, necessary tool for scaling human cooperation.
But, and this is the crux of the paper's transition into economics.
The paper isn't just describing what money does.
It is issuing a massive, mathematically rigorous warning about how it does it.
The author mathematically proved that this monetary projection functor is non-injective and non-isometric.
Those are critical mathematical properties.
We really need to unpack what happens when a projection is non-injective and non-isometric.
Let's start with non-injective.
I'll use an analogy for the listener to visualize what this means for data compression.
Imagine you have an incredibly high-resolution 3D movie file.
It has surround sound, 4K visuals, multiple language tracks, director's commentary, deep emotional
resonance.
It's a 100 gigabyte file.
That represents human reality, the full, rich, aggregate possibility structure.
Now imagine compressing that entire 100 gigabyte movie into a tiny, silent, heavily pixelated
2 megabyte GIF.
You are projecting from a high-dimensional space down to a low-dimensional space.
Exactly.
Now you can technically email that GIF across the world in a fraction of a second.
It is highly efficient for communication and coordination.
But the compression is profoundly lossy.
You have permanently lost the depth, the audio, the pacing, and the structural richness of
the original file.
And that loss is exactly what non-injective means in topology.
It means that multiple, entirely different complex inputs in the 3D space will be squashed
down and map onto the exact same simplified output in the 2D space.
The nuance is mathematically destroyed in the translation.
Right.
And non-isometric means that the actual distances, the relative importance and relationships of
things in the 3D space, are completely warped and distorted when you flatten them onto a 1D line.
Things that were far apart might look close together, and things that were connected might be severed.
What is terrifying here is the sociological implication of this math.
The paper called this consequence compression-induced equivalence.
Because the monetary metric squashes all these rich dimensions into a single scalar number,
two completely different human actions, with vastly different impacts on our actual lived
reality, can end up having the exact same monetary value.
Let's give the listener a concrete example of compression-induced equivalence in the real
world.
Let's think about the economy of a mid-sized town.
Okay, let's look at Action A.
A group of citizens starts a local cooperative grocery store.
They source food from local farmers, paying them fairly.
They provide healthy food to a food desert.
They train employees, creating deep social bonds and community resilience.
The structural richness of the town skyrockets.
The possibility spaces, the omega subs of everyone involved, expand beautifully.
But let's say the net monetary profit generated at the end of the year is, hypothetically, $100,000.
A highly complex, structurally rich process that outputs a scalar value of $100,000.
Now look at Action B.
A massive private equity firm buys up the only affordable housing complex in that exact same
town.
They evict half the tenants, double the rent for the rest, refuse to do maintenance, and
extract every possible cent.
This stress destroys families.
The community fabric is completely torn apart.
The structural richness of the town is severely degraded.
The possibility spaces of those renters physically shrink.
But the net monetary profit generated for the firm is also exactly $100,000.
Wow.
So, to the metric, to the projection functor of money, Action A and Action B are perfectly
mathematically equivalent.
The system is fundamentally blind to the difference between building a community and cannibalizing
it.
Precisely.
Because the metric only perceives the 1D scalar number, it cannot see the 3D structural destruction.
The nuance of the human possibility space is entirely invisible to the math of the market.
And as long as the market is the primary arbiter of reality, Action B is actually incentivized
because it's often faster to execute than Action A.
And the paper points out that this isn't just a philosophical complaint about capitalism.
It has mechanical, geometric consequences for the self.
Because if your identity is mathematically defined by your possibility space, and money
allows systemic actors to manipulate that aggregate space without seeing the damage they are doing,
then economic inequality isn't just about some people having fewer coins in their pocket.
No.
It is a violent structural reality.
The paper states that monetary inequality literally induces an asymmetry in the geometric
space of possibilities.
If you are subjected to extractive economic forces, your horizon, your omega sub T, physically
shrinks.
The actual branches of possible futures available to you are severed.
Your landscape becomes a narrow corridor.
Meanwhile, the possibility branches of the wealthy expand exponentially.
They are navigating a massive open world while you are trapped in a shrinking maze.
Which is a chilling realization.
Because if the monetary system is fundamentally blind to structural richness due to this lossy
compression, what happens when highly intelligent people aided by supercomputers learn to game
that blindness?
What happens when you build systemic machines designed entirely to exploit the gif at the
expense of the movie?
That leads us right into the paper's diagnosis of our current era.
Power, extraction, and inshittification.
This is where Fliction's framework becomes fiercely analytical about modern institutional dynamics.
To understand this, we have to start by redefining what power actually is.
Right, because usually when we talk about power, we just think of it as having the most money.
The person with the biggest bank account has the most power.
They can buy the most properties, hire the most lawyers, and win the game.
But the paper defines power completely differently.
In this mathematical model, power is a higher order operator.
Wealth is the ability to make choices within the existing game.
Power is the ability to change the topology of the game itself.
It is the ability to rewrite the roles of the possibility space.
If the economy is a massive board game, wealth is having the most pieces on the board.
Power is the ability to redraw the squares, change the rules of movement, and alter the
victory conditions while everyone else is still playing.
Exactly.
The paper formalizes power as a transformation operator that alters how possibilities are generated
or how the valuation metric itself is computed.
Power acts directly on the geometry of constraint.
When you combine this kind of structural power with a valuation metric that is fundamentally
blind to real-world richness, you get a toxic reaction.
You get what the paper calls extractive dynamics.
The author introduces a rigorous proof here called the process-projection power theorem.
It is mathematically dense, utilizing algebraic topology, but the conclusion is inescapable.
When a complex system is designed to optimize its behavior solely to increase a single compressed
scalar metric like corporate profits, GDP, or social media engagement time, it will systematically
favor transformations that increase that number while secretly destroying the underlying structural
richness of the system.
This is wild.
The paper is essentially mathematically proving that unregulated optimization in a complex
system inevitably leads to structural destruction.
It's not a bug.
It's a feature of the math.
Let's make this incredibly concrete for the listener, because the paper actually models a
phenomenon that has dominated the tech industry over the last decade.
It models in-shitification.
Yes.
The term was coined a few years ago by Corey D'Acaro, but Flickshian's paper formally models
in-shitification mathematically as extractive divergence.
Extractive divergence.
I want you, the listener, to think about your favorite social media platform or a search
engine or a food delivery app when it first launched.
Think about how amazing it was in the beginning.
In the early stages, the platform's proxy metric, let's say daily active users or click-through
rate, is closely correlated with actual genuine value.
People are using the app because it expands their possibility space, connects them with old
friends, it helps small businesses find customers, it provides accurate search results.
The metric and the structural richness are rising together in harmony.
The movie and the GIF are roughly showing the same picture, but then the platform goes public
or venture capital demands a 10x return.
The system suddenly demands relentless, infinite optimization.
The algorithm is given one single objective.
Make the scalar metric go up at all costs.
Increase engagement time.
Increase ad revenue.
Right.
And because of the blind spot we talked about, the fact that the metric can't actually see
richness, the algorithm realizes something dangerous.
It realizes it doesn't actually need to provide real human value to make the number go up.
Exactly.
The system discovers extractive divergence.
It figures out how to maximize the metric by cannibalizing the system's actual usefulness.
How does the math describe that?
I know the paper uses some heavy topology here.
What is actually happening under the hood when a platform inshittifies?
The paper proves mathematically that phantom value is created by depleting the system's
cohomological complexity.
Okay, cohomological complexity is a massive, intimidating term.
If you're listening right now and thinking that sounds like a graduate-level math seminar,
don't worry, let's ground this.
What is cohomology in this context?
In topology, cohomology is a way of measuring the deep, hidden structural integrity of a
space.
It measures the holes or the obstructions to local data patching together to form a coherent
global structure.
In a social or economic system, cohomological complexity represents the deep underlying foundation
of trust.
The reliability of the search results, the authenticity of the human connection, the security of the
data, it's the structural load-bearing walls of the community.
So, extractive divergence happens when the platform's algorithm figures out how to mine
those load-bearing walls and convert them into surface-level metrics.
Precisely.
Let me give you an analogy.
Imagine a family trying to survive a brutal winter in a large, beautiful house.
Their only metric for success, their single scalar number, is the thermostat reading in
the living room.
For a while, they do the hard work.
They chop firewood, they insulate the windows, and the house stays warm.
The metric correlates with reality.
Right.
But then, they get tired, or the metric demands a higher temperature faster than they can chop
wood.
So, they look around the room for a faster source of fuel.
Exactly.
They start chopping up the antique furniture and throwing it into the fire.
Then, they start tearing up the floorboards.
And what happens to the metric?
The fire roars.
The thermostat number spikes to 80 degrees.
According to their single 1D metric, they are incredibly successful.
They are richer in heat than ever before.
The stock price of the house is soaring.
What they are actually doing is systematically destroying the structural richness, the co-homological
complexity of their own home.
They are burning the furniture to satisfy the thermostat.
And the paper argues this isn't a mistake.
It is not a moral failing of a specific CEO or a glitch in the code.
It is a mathematical inevitability when you attempt to optimize a high-dimensional, complex
space using a single 1D scalar metric.
Goodhart's law states that when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.
Flickshon mathematically proves why Goodhart's law exists.
It is a structural law of physics applied to economics.
The platform gets richer on paper, but the user's space of possibilities progressively
narrows.
Think about it.
You open an app today, and instead of seeing posts from your friends or family, which is
what you actually want, you see an endless feed of algorithmically generated outrage baits,
sponsored drop-shipped products, an AI-generated slop designed purely to keep you scrolling
for three more seconds.
Your Omega Sub-T, your personal horizon of choice, has been artificially constrained by
the platform's power.
They are terraforming your preference fields, digging trenches of anger and anxiety just to
harvest your attention.
To harness the friction of your playhead.
They are feeding your limited, asymmetric experience of time into their symmetric optimization
machine.
You are experiencing the progressive and shittification of your own possibility space.
The gif is eating the movie.
I'm not going to lie, looking at the map of reality this way is incredibly grim.
We have a system where reality is a flow of choices, money compresses those choices blindly,
and power exploits that blindness to burn the furniture of society while the thermostat tells
us everything is great.
It feels like a diagnosis of a terminal disease for human civilization.
It would be if the paper stopped there.
Many critiques of capitalism or technology simply point out the flaws and throw up their
hands.
But what's truly remarkable about Fliction's work is that it doesn't just diagnose the disease.
It pivots entirely and spends the last hundred pages proposing a highly technical, mathematically
rigorous cure.
It asks the ultimate architectural question.
If compression and extraction are mathematical inevitabilities of our current metrics, how
do we build systemic architecture that does not self-destruct?
And that brings us to the most hopeful part of this deep dive.
The blueprint for a new system.
The mathematics of care and log sovereignty.
Now, I want to clarify something for the listener right away.
When I hear the word care, I usually think of a warm, fuzzy emotion.
Empathy, compassion, nursing someone back to health.
But the paper completely redefines this word, doesn't it?
It strips the sentimentality out of it.
It does.
It removes care from the realm of pure emotion and defines it formally as a structural imperative.
Care is mathematically defined as the act of maintenance, preservation, and increase of structural richness across time.
Let's unpack that definition.
What does it mean to structurally care for a system?
Care is the preservation of history, your H sub T, ensuring the truth of what has happened is not erased.
It is the expansion and diversity of possibility spaces, your omega sub T, ensuring people have more viable paths tomorrow than they do today.
And it is the integrity of preference fields, your size sub T, protecting people from having their psychological landscapes terraformed by extractive algorithms.
Care is the active, continuous thermodynamic work required to make sure the furniture doesn't get burned.
So, if extraction is taking a complex 3D world and violently crushing it down into a 1D number to make a quick buck, care is the exact opposite vector.
Care is the continuous effort of maintaining the 3D structure.
It's tending the community garden, repairing the soil, and nurturing the relationships instead of just paving the lot to maximize the parking toll.
Well, precisely. And the paper proves a crucial negative theorem here, which is a warning for anyone trying to fix society.
Care cannot be reduced to a single number or a scalar metric without instantly losing its essence.
Wait, explain that. Why can't we just measure care?
Because of the compression dynamics we just discussed, you cannot have a care score from 1 to 100.
You cannot solve the problems of capitalism by just inventing a social goodness coin or adding an ESG metric to the stock market.
The moment you compress care into a 1D scalar metric, you invite the exact same extractive dynamics.
The algorithms and the power structures will simply learn to gain the social goodness metric while continuing to burn the furniture underneath.
You can't fight Goodhart's law with more Goodhart's law.
If you make care a target metric, people will find a way to inshidify care.
Right. So, Fliction argues we need a fundamentally new computational and economic architecture.
We can't use the master's tools to dismantle the master's house.
The paper outlines three requirements for what it calls Caroline Systems.
Let's go through this blueprint.
If we were going to build a society or a digital platform based on this math, what is requirement number one?
Requirement number one is Caroline valuation.
We have to completely stop using flat 1D numbers to measure value.
The paper suggests moving to higher dimensional representations of value, utilizing what it calls sheaf theoretic structure.
Okay, another big mathematical term. Let's translate sheaf theoretic structure into something we can grasp.
What is a sheaf?
In mathematics, a sheaf is a tool that allows you to systematically track local data and glue it together into global data without ever losing the local nuances.
It tracks how things relate to each other across different spaces.
So, instead of a single price tag saying, this apple costs $1, how would a sheaf represent value?
Value has to be represented as a complex relational web.
Imagine if an economic transaction didn't just record the transfer of a scalar dollar amount, but computationally recorded the ecological impact on the soil, the social labor history of the farmer, the transportation carbon cost, and the nutritional density, all bound together in an unseverable data structure.
The metric itself must reflect the 3D richness of the real world.
It's like insisting that our systems can only communicate by sending the whole 100 gigabyte 3D movie file instead of the 2 megabyte GIF.
Yes, it's computationally heavier, it requires vastly more bandwidth, but it's actually true to reality.
It's mathematically immune to the blindness that causes extraction.
Exactly, which leads directly to requirement number two, care-constrained generation.
This sounds like a safety valve for progress.
It is a prophylactic requirement.
In our current system, you can launch a new product, deploy a new algorithmic trading bot, or build a new platform that actively destroys a local economy, and as long as it's legal and makes a profit, the system allows it.
The burden of proof is on society to clean up the mess later.
Care-constrained generation reverses this.
It means that any new action, protocol, or technology introduced into the system must mathematically prove, before it is allowed to execute, that it does not degrade the overall structural richness, the cohomological complexity of the aggregate space.
Wow. It's a mathematical do-no-harm principle hard-coded into the literal physics of the economy.
If your new algorithmic bot increases efficiency but lowers the structural integrity of the market, the system physically will not compile the code.
It rejects the transition.
Precisely. It filters out destructive causality before it can become history.
And finally, the third requirement is stabilized preference dynamics.
Right. This deals with the RSVP fields, the trenches we dig in our possibility spaces.
Yes. A Caroline system must include continuous corrective feedback loops.
If an actor, say, a monopolistic corporation is persistently engaging in extraction, if they are consistently narrowing the possibility horizons of the people around them to widen their own, the system mathematically penalizes them.
It actively increases the friction on their ability to act, slowing them down and stabilizing the aggregate space so others can recover.
Now, I have to stop here, because while this all sounds beautiful in theory, it sounds like a mathematically perfect utopian architecture.
The practical reality is terrifying.
How do you actually build this? Who enforces it?
Because if you put a central government or a single tech monopoly in charge of the care-constrained generation algorithm,
well, you've just created the ultimate authoritarian nightmare.
Whoever controls the math controls reality.
This is the exact danger Flixien addresses, and it raises the most practical,
revelationary implementation proposed in the entire paper, the log-sovereignty protocol.
Log-sovereignty.
This is the anchor that prevents the utopia from becoming a dystopia.
Let's dig into this.
Flixien recognizes that if you have a central database controlled by a corporation or a state,
that entity possesses power in the truest formal sense.
They have the power to rewrite the rules, rewrite the metrics, and rewrite history itself to suit their needs.
To stop platforms or states from manipulating our possibility spaces,
identity and truth cannot be subjective.
They must be anchored in something purely immutable.
And what is that anchor?
How do we establish objective truth in a fragmented world?
By anchoring it strictly to an append-only event log, the actual irreversible history of transitions.
Let me unpack log sovereignty for the listener,
because understanding the difference between a mutable database and an append-only log
is crucial to understanding the future of the internet.
Think about a typical database today, like your bank account or your social media profile.
The bank's central server says your current state is that you have $5,000.
But if a hacker or a corrupt bank executive or an oppressive government goes into that database
and changes that $5,000 to $0, the $5,000 is simply gone.
The system's truth is whatever the current state of the database says it is,
it is highly mutable.
Right.
And because it is mutable, because the truth can be overwritten by whoever has admin access,
it is profoundly vulnerable to capture, extraction, and inshittification.
But an append-only event log operates on a completely different paradigm.
It does not store a final state.
It only stores the immutable history of transitions, it says.
On Tuesday, you deposited $10,000.
On Thursday, you withdrew $5,000.
To figure out your current state, the system has to read the entire history from the very beginning.
And crucially, you can never, ever go back and erase the deposited $10,000 line.
You can only append a new line to the end of the log saying a correction was made.
Exactly.
It mimics the arrow of time.
And log sovereignty mandates that this history, the true causal sequence of events cryptographically
secured across a decentralized network, is the supreme and only authority.
No institutional operator, no CEO, and no politician can overwrite the past.
In this system, your identity isn't a fragile profile stored on a corporate server in Silicon
Valley.
Your identity is the cryptographic proof of your own historical trajectory.
If they can't rewrite your history, they can't invisibly narrow your future.
They can't manipulate your horizon without leaving a permanent, mathematically auditable
trail of exactly what they did.
Precisely.
And to make this massive, append-only architecture mathematically functional and computationally efficient,
the paper introduces a new computational grammar called SpherePop.
I have to say, amidst all the dense algebraic topology and category theory, SpherePop sounds
like a bubbly fruit soda, but it's actually a blueprint for a post-extractive computing paradigm.
It's a formal, operational grammar with three distinct commands.
Merge, collapse, and append.
We don't need to get bogged down in the symbolic logic of how the compiler works, but the core
philosophy of SpherePop is vital to everything we've discussed.
The guiding maxim of the language is, abstraction is projection, not erasure.
Abstraction is projection, not erasure.
What does that actually mean in practice for a software engineer building a CARA-lined system?
Think about how our current computing systems handle big data.
When a system needs to summarize data to make a fast calculation when it needs to abstract,
it usually deletes or abandons the underlying raw data to save server space and processing
power.
It collapses the complexity, creates the 1D metric, and throws away the original 3D reality.
SpherePop is designed so it never deletes.
So how does it compute anything quickly?
When it needs to simplify a massive, complex data set to make a quick decision, it creates
a collapse operation.
It projects the data down into a simpler form.
But the protocol mandates that it must maintain a permanent, unbreakable, cryptographic semantic
link back to the full, rich history of the data in the attend-only log.
So you get the speed and coordination of the 2D GIF, but you never actually throw away the
100 gigabyte 3D movie file.
The true history is always intact, always auditable, and always ready to be expanded back out if
the system needs to verify its structural richness or check if extraction is occurring.
Exactly.
It's a computational architecture where the preservation of history, which, remember, is the foundational
definition of the self and the core requirement of care, is hard-coded into the literal grammar
of the code.
The system physically cannot forget.
That is absolutely staggering.
It's essentially attempting to build a digital architecture that fundamentally respects the
first-person perspective of time.
It respects the irreversible arrow of reality, rather than treating data as a timeless, symmetrical
block of stuff that can be endlessly manipulated, deleted, and overwritten by whoever has the most
money or server space.
It is a profound, unified synthesis.
It connects the fundamental physics of time through the subjective experience of consciousness
directly to the architecture of software and macroeconomics.
It proves that they are not separate domains.
They are different expressions of the exact same continuous process.
Which brings us to the end of our journey today.
So what does this all mean for you, the listener, navigating your own complex, deeply fragmented
reality?
Let's synthesize everything we've explored over the last hour.
We started by looking at the deepest mysteries of time itself.
We learned that the universe isn't a static block of objects.
It's an endless, irreversible process of possibilities collapsing into history.
We saw how consciousness itself isn't a ghost in the machine, but simply the internal, first-person
experience of that exact transition.
The feeling of making a choice, feeling the friction of the playhead, and moving time forward.
We mapped out the geometry of the self.
You are not a static object.
You are mathematically defined by your irreversible history and the specific horizon of choices
available to you today.
And we learned that every choice you make physically digs gravitational trenches in your future,
deforming your path through RSVP field dynamics.
We examined what happens when millions of human beings try to coordinate those massive, complex
horizons.
We invent money, a lossy projection functor that violently squashes the 3D richness of
human life into a 1D scalar metric, creating a systemic blindness to the nuance of human
interaction.
And we saw the devastating mathematical consequences of that compression.
We saw how power exploits the blindness of the metric, how optimizing for the thermostat causes
institutions to burn the underlying furniture of our communities.
We explored the tragic mathematical inevitability of inshittification and extractive divergence.
But finally, we also saw the way out.
We explored the formal mathematics of CARE, the systemic architectural requirement and
preserve structural richness, rather than just blindly maximizing a scalar metric.
We looked at CARE-aligned valuation, where we stopped trying to flatten reality and embrace
sheath-theoretic complexity.
We looked at the log-sovereignty protocol, anchoring truth in an append-only history that
cannot be rewritten by corporate or state power.
And we looked at the sphere-pop grammar, ensuring that when we abstract reality to understand it,
we never erase the richness underneath.
Abstraction is projection, not erasure.
If I were to offer one profound summary statement reflecting the paper's ultimate
conclusion, it would be this.
Reality is irreversible becoming.
The deep disconnects we feel every single day, the gap between mind and matter, the painful
conflict between human value and market price, the friction between social coordination and
corporate extraction.
These aren't separate, isolated problems to be solved by different departments.
They are all fundamentally symptoms of the exact same underlying error.
They are what happens when we try to compress the rich, irreversible, subjective flow of time
into static, objective, manageable models.
We suffer because we continually mistake the map for the territory.
And worse, we let the people drawing the map dictate where we are allowed to walk.
Which leads me to a final thought I want to leave you with today.
Something for you to mull over as you turn off this audio, go back into the world, and navigate
your own possibility space.
Go for it.
If friction's math is right, if consciousness is truly just the internal first-person experience
of time's irreversible arrow, and if your self is mathematically defined by the rich, complex
branches of possibility you keep open, then I want you to think about the metrics that
currently govern your life.
Think about your credit score, your bank balance, the engagement metrics on your job performance
review, the view count on your social media posts, the GPA on your transcript.
Every single time you allow one of those flattened 1D metrics to dictate a choice you make, every
time you prune your own skill tree, alter your behavior, or dig a trench in your own possibility
space just to make a scalar number go up, are you just playing the game of economics?
Or, in a very real mathematical sense, are you actually compressing your own consciousness?
A haunting and mathematically essential question to ask ourselves.
Thank you so much for joining us on this incredibly deep dive.
As you move forward today, try to look past the numbers.
Embrace the uncompressible, unflattenable, structural richness of your own possibilities.
Keep your history intact, and keep your horizon wide open.
Take care.